Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection - Library Special Collections, ca. 1198-1616
UCLA Library Special Collections
Singer, S.W.
Smith, Arthur Barry
Sneyd, Rev. Walter
Stevens, Henry
Swaab, W.H.
Tiberi, Antonio
Tiberi, Bonzuano
Toffholz von Colberg, Karl Freiherr, H.H. Hauptmann
Townsend, George, earl of Leicester
Trostberg, count of. See Wolkenstein
Tucher von Simmelsdorf, C.A.
Uzielli, Giorgio
Varesi, Joseph, R.P.
Vegnauld, F. de
Von Feder Collection
Wakers(?), Anthonius
Walhers(?), See Wakers(?)
Welch, D'Alté A.
Wettengel, Christopher
Wilhelmus Wismeers(?), See Wismeers(?), Wilhelmus
William Jacob, priest in Pufflick, near Utrecht
Wismeers(?), Wilhelmus
Wolkenstein and Trostberg, count of
Zeitlin, Jacob
Zeitlin, Josephine
Zuan Maria Baldana
Institutions and Places Asscoiated with the Manuscripts
Albani Library
“Archivio Sornmi Picenardi,”
Avila, Bernardine nuns of St. Mary
Besançon, abbey of Billy
Buren, Society of Jesus
Buxheim, Carthusians
Cologne, Carthusians of St. Barbara
Delft, Augustinian nuns of St. Agnes
Ebersberg, Benedictines of St. Sebastian
Erfurt, Carthusians
Ferrara, Cistercians of San Bartolo
Fondi, abbey of S. Onofrio
Huys, Benedictines
Liesborn, Benedictines
London, St. Bride Foundation Typographical Library
Mainz, Jesuit College
Mechelen (Malines), Convent of Bethanie
Orders, religious: Augustinians
Benedictines
Carthusians
Celestines, Carthusians, Celestines, Cistercians, Dominicans, Franciscans, Society of Jesus
Ostberg, Brethren of the Cross
Paris, Celestines
“Picenardi, Archivio Sommi.” See “Archivio Sommi Picenardi”
St. Christopher, Carthusian house near Ferrara
St. Emmeram, Benedictines
Ste-Croix-sous-Offémont (Île de France), Celestines
Salem, near Heidelberg, Cistercians
Salzburg, Benedictines of St. Peter
S. Maria degli Angeli, Dominican nuns
Sulmona, Franciscans of S. Niccolò
Teruel, confraternity of St. Julian
Uekerath (archdiocese of Cologne), parish church
Vatican Library
Form of Entry
The format used in the descriptions follows that employed by N.R. Ker in Medieval Manuscripts in British Libraries, 3 vols. (Oxford 1969-1983).
1. HEADING. Each entry begins with library and call number, figure number (if any) in this catalog, author and brief title, and place and date. The place and date, when not specified in the manuscript, have been determined by style of script and decoration and, when applicable, by external evidence. Place names refer to geographical regions, rather than to modern political entities. The sigla used for the dates of the manuscripts are on this model: s. XIIIin (saeculo XIII ineunte) for the beginning of the thirteenth century; s. XIII1 for the first half of the century; s. XIIImed (sacculo XIII medio) for the middle of the century; s. XIII2 for the second half of the century; s. XIIIex (saeculo XIII exeunte) for the end of the century; s. XIII-XIV for the turn of the thirteenth to the fourteenth century.
2. CONTENTS. In the case of composite volumes (volumes of two or more originally separate books subsequently bound together), the original books are described first in their contents, then in their physical aspect under roman numerals I and II (etc.). Within the contents section of all manuscripts, the text is broken into arabic-numbered sections for case of reference; the numbered sections, which were fixed by the compilers of this catalog do not always correspond to obvious divisions in the manuscripts (e.g., in long series of prayers in devotional books). A folio is referred to by a numeral alone if a recto is intended, and by a numeral with a lower case “v” for a verso; the form “f. 1r-v” means that both recto and verso of that leaf are considered; “a” and “b” refer to the first and the second column on a given page. In transcription, all abbreviations have been expanded silently. Square brackets signal an offered but uncertain transcription, enclosing either the doubtful words, word, or part of word, or a question mark which refers to the immediately preceding word. Angle brackets occur where no solution for the difficulty is attempted; they may enclose a question mark or a reason for the complete illegibility, such as “<damaged>.” The spelling of the manuscript has been preserved, with “[sic]” added only when the form of the word seemed unlikely or such as to cause the reader to suspect a typographical error. We have retained the manuscripts' ę/e/æ, as they show relative distance from classical Latin; i/j, however, have been uniformly rendered as i; u/v have been distinguished according to modern use for ease of reading. Proper nouns are capitalized. Rubrics, whether in red ink, underlined, in a display script, or merely distinguished from the main body of the text by a space, are here rendered in italics. In the case of the series of brief texts or excerpts in patristic miscellanies, we have given only the rubric (omitting incipit and explicit of the text); in the case of series of prayers, we have preferred, as an aid to identification, to give a slightly longer incipit and no explicit, since the prayers tend to end with long, and frequently interchangeable, formulas. In liturgical books, saints' names are generally given in the form used by F.G. Holweck, A Biographical Dictionary of the Saints (St. Louis, 1924), a convenient standard. A double diagonal slash // means that a text begins or ends defectively; ellipses signal omitted text. Following each numbered section of the text, where applicable, is a brief bibliographical notice of editions, of lists of manuscripts, of identifying number in the appropriate repertory (e.g., Schneyer, Stegmüller, Walther).
3. PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION. This is arranged in roughly the order in which the book was produced. The term “parchment” is used throughout for all animal skins, since the traditional distinction between parchment and vellum seems to have been based more on quality of preparation than on knowledge of biological differences between sheepskin and calfskin. For manuscripts on paper, we have attempted to identify watermarks according to their similarity, or least dissimilarity, to the tracings in Briquet. The number of leaves is in roman numerals for endleaves, arabic for those of the book itself. Measurements are in millimeters: first, height and width of the book; then, in parentheses, height and width of the ruled space. The numbers are, of course, approximations, since within any book there is considerable variation; we have preferred to measure ruled rather than written space, because it seemed to offer more consistency. The collation uses arabic numerals for the gatherings, with the number of leaves in that gathering in a suprascript arabic numeral; irregularities are given in parentheses, with the number showing the position in the quire of the irregular leaf; thus 18( - 6) means a quire of eight leaves of which the sixth is missing; 18( + 9) means that the quire of eight leaves has a leaf added in the ninth position, i.e. at the end. Ruling is specified as to device used or color (hard or dry point; lead, i.e. in a scratching gray or black; crayon, i.e. in a scratchy brown; ink; pale red ink); owner-produced manuscripts were often frame ruled, with no horizontal lines to guide the copyist. An effort has been made to distinguish the number of copyists and the leaves copied by each. Scripts are identified by a relatively restricted and simple nomenclature. As regards decoration, the height of initials is given in number of vertical lines of text space occupied; colors are mentioned summarily since their names are too subjective to be of value. The subjects of the miniatures have been given in brief terms and, in the case of liturgical books and particularly books of hours, tied to the text to which they belong, since the two function as a cohesive unit. The binding statement is somewhat more expansive for medieval or renaissance bindings than for early modern or modern bindings.
4. PROVENANCE. This section deals with the origin and subsequent ownership of the manuscript. In it we have summarized the evidence regarding date and place of origin given in the contents and physical description sections.
5. A SECUNDO FOLIO reference (the opening words of the second leaf) is supplied for manuscripts that may have belonged to an institution in the Middle Ages and thus have been listed in a medieval inventory.
6. BIBLIOGRAPHY. The bibliography cited here refers to the manuscript as a whole, rather than to its parts.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 1193313
Container List
- The Elmer Belt Library of Vinciana
  The Belt Library is a collection of manuscripts and printed books pertaining to Leonardo da Vinci and the Italian Renaissance. Assembled by Dr. Belt, the library was moved from his office to the UCLA campus in 1961, and to its present location within the Art Library in the Dickson Art Center in 1966. Portions of the collection remained with Dr. Belt, among them the fifteenth-century French lectionary described in Bond and Faye, Supplement, p.16. The library houses a collection of incunabula and a group of renaissance manuscripts. Besides the materials included below, the Belt Library possesses a seventeenth-century manuscript containing an anonymous treatise in Italian, Modo di fortificare (Belt 72). On the structure and history of the library, see F.L. Finger, Catalogue of the Incunabula in the Elmer Belt Library of Vinciana (Los Angeles, 1971), and Max Marmor, “The Elmer Belt Library of Vinciana,” The Book Collector, vol.38 (1989) pp.321-342.
  - LEONARDO DA VINCI, TRATTATO DELLA PITTURA. Italy, 1582., BELT LIBRARY 35.; Paper, ff. i + 105 + i; 297 × 210 (240 × 140) mm. 27 long lines. Written by one hand in late Italic script; illustrated. The compiler of this manuscript has been identified as Gregorio Pagani, and the date 1582 has been found on the excised second leaf of the manuscript, now in the Uffizi Gallery in Florence, drawing no.10506. For a fuller description, see Pedretti, cited below.; Bound in marbled paper over paste boards (s. XIX).
    ff. 1-105v: [title page] Discorsi di Lionardo da Vinci sopra la pittura; f. 2, an illustration, missing; ff. 3-96v [text] Il giovane debbe prima... sono dopo te; f. 97, errata; f. 97v blank; ff. 98-105v, table of contents; f. 106r-v blank.
    For the editions of this work see Steinitz, cited below. The Belt Library owns five other manuscript copies from later centuries (s. XVII-XIX), Manuscripts 33, 34, 36, 40, and 41; cf. Steinitz, no.83-90, 129-134.
    Written in Italy in 1582. “J. Bardzhus” (s. XIX) is written inside the back cover.
    Bibliography:
    K. Trauman Steinitz, Leonardo da Vinci's Trattato della Pittura, Treatise on Painting: A Bibliography of the Printed Editions, 1651-1956.. ., Library Research Monographs 5 (Copenhagen, 1958) pp.67-70.
    C. Pedretti, Leonardo da Vinci: Studies for a Nativity and the “Mona Lisa Cartoon” with Drawings after Leonardo from the Elmer Belt Library of Vinciana: Exhibition in Honour of Elmer Belt, M.D., on the Occasion of His Eightieth Birthday. Catalogue, UCLA Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies Publication 6 (Los Angeles, 1973) p.47.
  - MICHELANGELO BUONARROTI, RECORD. Italy, 1533., BELT LIBRARY 65.; Paper, 1 leaf; 43 × 160 mm. 5 long lines, in the hand of Michelangelo. Pasted on a larger sheet which bears the round stamp “Archivio Sommi Picenardi” and a note by Pio Martinucci, “Autografo di Michelangelo Buonarroti, come risulta dal confronto eseguito sul codice num. 3211 esistente in questa biblioteca, il quale contiene le poesie ed alcune lettere scritte di mano di quell'illustre personaggio. In fede. Dalla Biblioteca Vaticana li 15 marzo 1869, Pio Martinucci Secondo Custode,” with round stamp of the Vatican Library. On the verso of the supporting sheet, “Questo ricordo è stato pubblicato dal cav. Gaetano Milanesi a pag. 604 del suo libro: Le lettere di Michelangelo Buonarroti pubblicate coi Ricordi ed i contratti artistici, Firenze, Le Monnier, 1872; e da Aurelio Gotti, a pagina 225 del volume I° dell' opera: Vita di Michelangelo Buonarroti narrata con l'ajuto di nuovi documenti, Firenze, Tip. della Gazzetta d'Italia, 12 sett. 1875.”
    recto: Nel mille cinquecento trenta tre. Ricordo come oggi adì 22 di sectembre andai a Santo Miniato al Tedesco a parlare a papa Clemente che andava a Nnizza e in tal dì mi lasciò frate Sebastiano del Piombo un (?) suo cavallo.
    Edited by L. Bardeschi and P. Barocchi, I Ricordi di Michelangelo (Florence, 1970) p.278, no.253. They cast doubt on the authenticity of this ricordo, believing that the original was lost; they print the text from Milanesi, cited below.
    Gift of Jacob and Josephine Zeitlin, Los Angeles, in honor of Dr. Elmer Belt's eightieth birthday in 1973.
    Milanesi, cited above; Gotti, cited above; “Special Gifts in Honor of Elmer Belt,” UCLA Librarian vol.26 (1973) pp.22-23, plate p.21.
  - DEED NOTARIZED BY PIETRO DI ANTONIO DI SER PIETRO DA VINCI. Italy (Florence), 1459., BELT LIBRARY 66.; Parchment roll, made of two skins sewn together; 842 × 230 mm. Written in a current notarial hand, with the notary's sign across the seam and at the end. On the verso a contemporary register, and an archival note (s. XVIII) in Italian: “Contratto 1458, 8 novembre. A.I.N° 32. Niccolao di Giovanni e Michele di Ugo Vecchietti venderono a Guglielmo Rucellai una casa per rogo di Ser Piero di Antonio da Vinci negli 8 novembre 1458.”
    recto: Deed of sale of a house in Florence contracted between Niccolò Giovanni and Michele sons of Ugo di Niccolò de Vecchiettis, and Guglielmo Rucellai. The roll contains the records of the previous acts, begun on 8 November 1458, which led to the final deed on 3 May 1459, “Actum Florentie in populo Sancti Pancratii ac in domo infrascripti Guglielmi cardinalis de Oricellariis.” Notary: Pietro di Antonio di ser Pietro da Vinci, “civis et notarius florentinus imperiali auctoritate iudex ordinarius notariusque publicus,” and father of Leonardo da Vinci.
    Gift of the Friends of the Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies in honor of Dr. Elmer Belt's eightieth birthday in 1973.
    “Special Gifts in Honor of Elmer Belt,” UCLA Librarian, vol.26 (1973) p.21.
  - PETRUS DE CRESCENTIIS, RURALIUM COMMODORUM LIBRI. Italy (Bergamo), 1466., BELT LIBRARY 67.; Fig. 21; Parchment (ff. 1, 10) and paper (Cercle, not found in Briquet), ff. iii (modern) + 203 + iiii (modern); 312 × 215 (205/222 × 140) mm. 1-810 98 1010 119 (no gap in text) 12-2010 216; vertical catchwords, occasionally touched with red at the beginning. 40/42 long lines; bounding lines ruled in lead; text ruled in pale yellow ink. Written in semi-cursive humanistic script with gothic influence; olive brown ink. On f. 1, 8-line initial in purple inhabited by a bust of the author on blue background highlighted in white, in a square gold frame with red, green, and blue conventional foliage extending to the inner and upper margin; in the lower margin, arms in a wreath supported by blue and red leafy branches; 5-line and 2-line initials in plain red, at times with brown flourishes; text initials occasionally touched with red; titles in red minuscule. Extensive contemporary marginalia (particularly in the sections on viticulture on ff. 55v-64v) by at least three hands, one of which enters the note on f. 203r-v. f. 203v is stained and faded; slight mildew damage; last folios show insect damage.; Tooled dark morocco binding (Lothian Library binding) by “Orrock binder Edin.” (s. XIX); on the front and back covers, “L” surmounted by a crown; pastedowns and flyleaves in marbled paper; gilt edges.
    1) ff. 1-203: Incipit liber ruralium commodorum a domino Petro de Crescentiis cive Bononie ad honorem omnipotentis Dei et serenissimi regis Karoli et ad utilitatem omnium gentium compilatus. Cum ex virtute prudentie que inter bonum et malum... cum avibus domesticatis et retibus diversis et visco. Explicit liber de ruralibus commodis editus a magistro Petro de Cresentiis bononiense et scriptus per me Iohannem filisi [sic] domini Benalii de Benaliis anno currente 1466. Et est domini Benalii de Benaliis civis Pergami et finitus fuit die 20 decembris [Hain no.5826-5832; GW no.7820-7825].
    2) f. 203r-v: [note on wine] Ad liberandum vinum cum tota vegete simul et semel ab omni corruptione in omnibus diebus natalibus... quam optimum est contra ebrietatem et est medicina de caulibus et se cor... (?).
    Written for Benalio Benali of Bergamo (his arms on f. 1 bottom: gules, in chief a chevron argent between two cocks argent) by his son Giovanni in 1466; perhaps they are kinsmen of the Bergamo printer-editor Bernardino Benali (ca. 1458-ca. 1543), concerning whom see the Dizionario biografico degli italiani vol.8 (1966) pp.165-167. Belonged in the nineteenth century to the marquis of Lothian: vertical note “Marquis of Lothian” in the outer margin of f. 1, shelfmark “e.5.25” in the upper margin, Lothian binding. Given by the Samuel Kress Foundation and a group of friends of Dr. Elmer Belt in honor of his eightieth birthday in 1973.
    Secundo folio: et debelitat nervos
  - SUPPOSED HOLOGRAPH OF RAFFAELLO SANZIO CONCERNING THE BUILDING OF ST. PETER'S IN ROME; SUPPOSED HOLOGRAPH ORDER OF GIULIANO LENO TO THE NOTARY FRANCESCO VIGOROSIS CONCERNING THIS UNDERTAKING. s. XIX?, BELT LIBRARY 68.; Paper, 295 × 220 mm.; f. 1, 24 lines with four signatures; f. 2, 11 lines and signature. In the upper righthand corners, foliation by a later hand: f. 1, “279”; f. 2, “280.”
    1) f. 1: Yhesus. Facio fede io Raphaello di Gioanni Santi d'Urbino architectore de Santo Piero come maestro Francisco di Domenicho Bonello si convene con Messer Iuliano Leno churatore... Io Raphaello ut supra. [Signatures:] Io Domenicho di Francesco Bonello convengo et prometo come di sopra è schritto; Iuliano Leno manu propria; F[rancesco] Vigorosis not[arius] subscripsi.
    2) f. 2. Messer Francesco Vigorosis pigliarete una obligatione da messer Domenico Bonello... in li termini de prima. Die 1 augusti 1514. Iuliano Leno manu propria.
    Both documents are edited with facsimiles by S. Ray, “Il 'gran peso sopra le spalle': Raffaello e la Basilica Vaticana,” L'Architettura, cronache e storia vol.18, no.199 (May 1972) pp.58-60. Among the various anomalies displayed by these two documents, it is not clear that the two signatures (ff. 1, 2) purporting to be those of Iuliano Leno are written by the same hand; it is noteworthy also that Domenico di Francesco Bonello has become “Francesco di Domenico Bonello” in the supposed Raphael text. Concerning the authenticity, see most recently C. L. Frommel, “Die Peterskirche unter Papst Julius II. in Licht neuer Dokumente,” Römisches Jahrbuch für Kunstgeschichte vol.16 (1976) pp.57-136 at 80 no.81.1
    The leaves were in Rome ca. 1865, in Major Kühlen's possession. Given to the American banker Joseph W. Hambuechen, when he left Florence to return to America before World War II; in the possession of Karl Loevenich, New York, in 1972. Gift of Lawson Ridgeway to the Belt Library in 1975.
    1. We thank John Shearman for this reference; Professor Shearman will challenge the authenticity of a large group of such documents in a forthcoming study.
  - BARTOLOMEO AMMANNATI, LETTER TO FRANCESCO BUSINI. Italy (Florence), 10 February 1570., BELT LIBRARY 70.; Paper, 1 leaf; 290 × 205 mm. 14 lines and signature. Address: “Al molto Magnifico Messer Francesco Busini proveditore di loro altezze. In Pisa.”
    recto: Magnifico Messer Francesco honorando, Io ho ricevuto la letera di Vostra Signoria et ò scritto a messer Giovanni Cacini... senza fine mi racomando. Di Firenze, agli x di febraio 1570, di vostra Signoria amorevole Bartolomeo Amannati.
    Holograph; dealing with timber and marbles needed for his work. Concerning Bartolomeo Ammannati see Dizionario biografico degli italiani vol.2 (1960) pp.798-801.
    Gift of E. Maurice Bloch, professor in the Department of Art at UCLA, in 1974. Part of the same gift are Belt 69 (Francesco Albani, Letter to Girolamo Bonnini, Bologna, 20 July 1658) and Belt 71 (Giovanni Mannozzi, called Giovanni da S. Giovanni, Letter, dated Rome, May 1626).
  - BREVIARY. s. XVIII-XIX(?)., BELT LIBRARY 73.; Parchment, 1 framed leaf (the verso is not accessible); 550 × 395 (365 × 260) mm., 11 long lines + 2 staves; 520 × 375 mm. including the illuminated border; ruled in plummet. Large and heavy rounded gothic bookhand in liturgical style (littera textualis formata); black ink rather faded off. Full border with floral pattern and acanthus leaves, fruits, birds, vases on purple background; primary initial (4-line) in four colors on black and gold background; secondary initials in three colors (purple, blue, green) with floral pattern on gold background; tertiary initials in gold on purple and blue background, highlighted with white; initials in the text with elaborate black scrolls touched with green and yellow; rubrics in red minuscule; music in square notation on staves of four red lines.
    Fig. 36
    recto: // ardor proximos... Ant.... Deduc me domine... Psalmus. Legem pone mihi... in toto corde meo // [Ant. in festis per annum ad tertiam in the Roman breviary; Ps. 118.33-34].
    The framed leaf is described in typewritten catalog of the Norton Simon Foundation Gift (1966) as follows: “A page of an Antiphonal... by Fra Antonio da Monza... From the Rodolphe Kann collection, Paris 1907. From the collection of Archer Huntington who inherited it from his mother Mrs. Collis P. Huntington.” The piece probably dates from the eighteenth or nineteenth century, an attempt to imitate sixteenth -century Italian style. The size and style of script are unusual for the text of a breviary. The full border illumination seems out of place for a page containing no relevant incipit, but simply one of the many psalms for the ordinary office. The frame with glass prohibits a closer investigation of both sides of the leaf.
- The Charles E. Young Research Library: Department of Special Collections.
  The library's collection of western European medieval and renaissance manuscripts, only a small portion of the manuscript materials housed in the Department of Special Collections, is steadily growing. The increase is obvious from a comparison of 1) the list of manuscripts possessed by the department in the 1950s, as recorded by Bond and Faye, Supplement, pp.538-539; 2) the number of manuscripts cataloged here; and 3) the list, below, of further acquisitions in the years since this catalog was made, 1978-1990. For the most part, the present catalog describes every manuscript written before 1600. Given their diplomatic nature, this was impossible to do for both the large Orsini Archive (Collection 902, Boxes 1-532) and the smaller Italian Diplomatic Collection (Collection 100, Boxes 113-114), which are reported summarily below; typewritten inventories are available in the Department of Special Collections. Among the literary (nondocumentary) materials, this catalog at times includes manuscripts written after 1600, when the texts present some peculiar interest (see 170/282, *170/380) or, in one case, when it seemed worthwhile rectifying data given in the De Ricci Census (see 170/87).